<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Comfort in affliction, or, Advice to Protestant dissenters in times of persecution together with remarks on the just judgments of God upon this city and land, since the prohibition of the Gospel, by mulcts and penalties / by J.O.</title>
            <author>J. O.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53406</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32241</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12567480</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12567480</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63373</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53406)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63373)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1022:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Comfort in affliction, or, Advice to Protestant dissenters in times of persecution together with remarks on the just judgments of God upon this city and land, since the prohibition of the Gospel, by mulcts and penalties / by J.O.</title>
                  <author>J. O.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>19 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Jones,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Religious tolerance --  England.</term>
               <term>Persecution --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63373:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Comfort in Affliction, OR ADVICE TO PROTESTANT DISSENTERS IN Times of Perſecution, TOGETHER WITH Remarks on the juſt Judgments of God upon this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Land, ſince the Prohibition of the Goſpel, by Mulcts and Penalties.</p>
            <p>By <hi>J. O.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>R. Jones.</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:63373:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:63373:2"/>
            <head>COMFORT in AFFLICTION, OR ADVICE TO PROTESTANT DISSENTERS, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THE Suppreſſing the Glorious Light of the Goſpel, and Baniſhing it out of Publique View; the ſilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the Grace of Chriſts own Lips, and cauſing the Joyful Sound that Proclaims the Acceptable Year of the Lord, to ceaſe out of our Borders is the Evil of Evils, and the Miſery of Miſeries which brings all other Evils and Miſeries along with it; yea this ſhuts up the Kingdom of Heaven from the World, and ſets Hell wide open, for all men to run headlong into it, as we ſee it done this day. This exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des the Love, Mercy and Goodneſs of God from the World as much as poſſibly it can, and brings in his Wrath and heavy Diſpleaſure to waſt and conſume it, of which we have had the ſad and moſt exquiſite Experience, now alas! for ſeveral years together. For ſince the Goſpel, under ſeveral Mulcts and Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties, hath been forbidden to be Preach'd how many Manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations of Gods Juſt Anger have we ſeen in many ſtrange and unuſual Prodigies, in the Heavens, in the Waters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing loud Warnings of the Wrath to come. What a griveous and deſolating Plague, the Scourge of the Almighty hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed Thouſands and Ten Thouſands in that late great City, and in many other parts of the Nation, the like whereunto hath not been heretofore? What a dreadful Conflagration hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured that Famous and Incomparable City the Head and Glory of theſe Nations, and laid it in Aſhes and Ruines like <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorah;</hi> which Cities were ſet on Fire from Heaven, but this from Hell, by the Locuſts of the Bottomleſs Pit, the Emiſſaries of the Pope and his Clergy, which Vermin have ſwarmed in this Nation, ſince the removal of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>And this provoking Sin, is not ſo much the Sin of the people, as of Evil Counſellors at the Helm, who as it were, have openly renounced <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and deſired <hi>Barabbas</hi> to be given to them in his ſtead: they have rejected the ſweet and Meek Goſpel of Chriſt, and have deſired to be given to them the Cruel and Murderous Religion of <hi>Antichriſt.</hi> And this one thing carrys weight in it, that they who tolerate <hi>Popery</hi> to take its eaſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, and to lengthen its Cords, and to ſtrengthen its Stakes, though it be directly againſt Chriſt; and they who tolerate the open exerciſe of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Religion, which denies and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemes
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:63373:3"/>Chriſt, will by no means ſuffer nor endure the true and ſincere Goſpel of Chriſts Kingdom to be publiſhed, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der great Penalties.</p>
            <p>From hence follows the greateſt and deepeſt ignorance of God and Chriſt that can be, and of all their unſearchable Riches which the Goſpel hath diſcovered to the World. The greateſt ignorance of the Law and of Goſpel, of Sin and of Righteouſnes, of Salvation and Damnation, of Heaven and Hell; in a word, the groſſeſt ignorance of all the Revealed Truths of God, which concern us either to obtain Eternal Life, or to avoid Endleſs Death.</p>
            <p>Never was there ſuch a Deluge of Sin ſeen upon Earth, as now covers the Face of the Nation; this is even become the covering of all Fleſh. All ſorts of People, of High and Low Degree, whether Secular or Eccleſiaſtical, are all drencht and dyed in it; in ſuch ſort, that Men live in this World in the manifeſt likeneſs of the Devil, and if Satan himſelf were In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnate, you could not eaſily diſcern one from the other. They ſet their Faces againſt Heaven, and call out upon God to Damn them, Soul and Body. So Diveliſh they are, that they would fain be tormented before their time, and do often provoke Hell to ſwallow them up; for becauſe they can be no liker to the Devil in this World, they would haſten to Hell that there they may be fully like him. Oh Monſters of Mankind! Oh the true Seed of the Serpent! the right <hi>Generation of Vipers!</hi> Ye have been fore-warn'd by God to flee from the Wrath to come, but who hath warn'd you to flee unto it? Who among the remote Nations would believe the report of all your Villanies? The very rehearſal of them would put them into Pangs, and the bare hearing of them into Tremblings: their Sayings and Doings are ſuch, as are not fit to be mentioned or recited among Men, but onely in the midſt of Devils. For who without horrible fear, could either repeat or hear their deſperate Blaſphemies againſt God himſelf, glorious in Holineſs, and againſt our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, (whom God hath made his Firſt-Born. <hi>Higher than the Kings of the Earth;</hi> and <hi>when he brought him into the World, he ſaid, Let all the Angels Worſhip Him</hi>) and againſt the Holy Spirit (againſt whom <hi>whoever ſpeaks a word, it ſhall never be forgiven him</hi>) againſt the bleſſed Goſpel the great and onely <hi>Power of God to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi>) againſt the Kingdom of God on Earth, and againſt them that dwell in Heaven. Therefore, O Lord, forgive them not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For their Vine is as the Vine of</hi> Sodom, <hi>and of the Fields of</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrah, <hi>their Grapes are Grapes of Gall, their Cluſters are bitter, their Wine is the Poyſon of Dragons, and the cruel Venome of Aſps, The ſhew of their Countenance doth witneſs againſt them, and they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare their Sin more than</hi> Sodom, <hi>they hide it not, they boaſt of it, and every Man is famous as he can do moſt wickedly. Wo unto their Souls, for they have rewarded evil againſt themſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:63373:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>For therefore Hell hath enlarged her ſelf, and opened her Mouth without meaſure, and their Glory, and their Multitude, and their Pomp, and he that rejoiceth ſhall ſoon deſcend into it. This their Day approacheth, it comes, it makes haſt, when they ſhall periſh for ever like their own Dung, and they that have ſeen them ſhall ſay, where are they?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And therefore howl ye Profane Ones, for the Day of the Lord is at hand, it ſhall come as a Deſtruction from the Almighty: then ſhall your Wicked Hands fall down, and your Proud Hearts melt, and you ſhall be ſorely afraid; Pangs and Sorrow ſhall take hold on you, even Pangs as of a Woman in Travel: and when ye ſhall look to one another ye ſhall be amazed at one another, and your faces ſhall alter and change colour as Flames. For behold the Day of the Lord cometh cruel, both with Wrath and fierce Anger, to lay the Land deſolate for your ſakes, and he ſhall deſtroy the Sinners thereof out of it. And he will puniſh the World for their evil, and the Wicked for their wickedneſs, he will make the Arrogancy of the Proud Ones to c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſe, and will lay low the Haughtineſs of the Terrible Ones. In that day</hi> Sodom <hi>and</hi> Gomor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah <hi>ſhall riſe up in Judgment againſt you, and it ſhall be more tolerable for them than for you,</hi> O Ye Profane Ones of <hi>England!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Spiritual Evils preſs us ſore; As for our Outward Evils, they are well known and felt by All, of all ſorts; and though I ſhould be ſilent in the rehearſing them, they ſpeak forth them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. They are a ſore not to be touched; yet if no hand ſhould touch them, how ſhould they be healed? Wherefore I will in the Name and Fear of God make mention of one of them, and of ſuch an one as briefly comprehends all the reſt.</p>
            <p>And this is, The ſtrange and diſmal Withering, Waſting, Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing and Dying Condition of Poor <hi>England,</hi> whoſe common Welfare no Man now looks after or regards. Oh <hi>England!</hi> where are now thy Wiſe Men? where are thy Pilots? where are thy Phyſicians? where are thy Counſelors? where are thy Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers? where are they that pity thee, and ſay, <hi>Alas, Alas Poor England!</hi> thy Husband hath rejected thee, as a Wife of Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and thou art become a Widow of Sorrows: thou art left as a Cottage in a Vineyard; <hi>as a Lodge in a Garden of Cucumbers, as a Beſieged City. Thy bruiſe is incureable, and thy wound is grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous. There is none left to plead thy Cauſe, that thou mighteſt be bound up: thou hast no healing Medicines left thee; Fear and a Snare and the Pit are upon thee, and to whom wilt thou ſtretch forth thy hands, to whom wilt thou lift up thy Voice for help?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou waſt lately a Rich and Flouriſhing Kingdom, and for thy Plenty, Wealth and Glory waſt both the Wonder and Envy of the World. Whilſt thou didſt enjoy the Preſence of God, through his Word and Ordinances; whilſt Iniquity was baniſh'd out of Publique View; whilſt Holineſs and Righteouſneſs, Juſtice and Judgment, Truth and Equity had their chief place in thee, <hi>Thou waſt a People ſaved by the Lord,</hi> Honoured by the Lord, Exalted,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:63373:4"/>Magnified, Protected by the Lord. <hi>Thou waſt the Head and not the Tail, even the Glory of Kingdoms and Nations.</hi> Our Land then, was bleſſed with the precious things of Heaven, with the dew and the deep that coutcheth beneath, with the precious fruits brought forth by the Sun, and with the precious things put forth by the Moon, with the precious things of the Earth, and the Fulneſs thereof. We had plenty of Gold, and of Jewels of fine Gold; and our Houſes were ſtored with Silver; our Barns and Store-houſes were repleniſhed, and we were plenteous in Goods; in the fruit of our Cattel, and in the fruit of our Ground. Our Sons were as Plants grown up in their Youth, our Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters as poliſht Pillars; our Oxen were ſtrong to labour, and our Sheep brought forth Thouſands: we did eat our Bread with joy, and drank our Wine with a merry heart, becauſe God accepted our Works. Yea then the Firſt-Born of the Poor did feed, and the Needy did ly down in Safety; for there was no breaking in nor going out, nor complaining in our Streets. We were a happy People that were in ſuch a caſe, yea much more happy, becauſe God was our Lord.</p>
            <p>And thou O <hi>London,</hi> (for my heart is towards thee, and I am diſtreſſed for thee O <hi>London,</hi> and pained at the very heart) Thou waſt a Joyous City, whoſe Antiquity was of Ancient Days; thou waſt the Crowning City, whoſe Merchants were Princes, whoſe Traff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquers were the Honourable of the Earth: by thy great Wiſdom, and by thy Traffique thou didſt get thee Riches, and thou didſt get Gold and Silver into thy Treaſuries. The Harveſt of the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was thy Revenue, and thou waſt the Mart of Nations. All Nations emptied their Delicacies into thy Boſom, and poured forth their pleaſant things into thy Lap. And when thy Wares went forth out of thy Seas, thou filledſt many People, thou didſt enrich the Kings of the Earth with the multitude of thy Riches, and of thy Merchandiſe. Thou waſt alſo the Mountain of God, thou hadſt, in the midſt of thee, the ſtones of Fire. Thou waſt the chief High-Place; the Miniſters of Jeſus were dear to thee, and thy Arms were always open to embrace them; thou didſt fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent the Solemn Aſſemblies of the Saints, with the Multitude of them that kept right Holy-Day. The Out-caſts of Chriſt were wont to dwell with thee, and thou waſt a Covert to them from the face of the Spoiler. Many Fatherleſs Children had harbour and ſuccour in thee, and thou waſt a Husband to the Widows. It was thy Meat and Drink to feed the hungry, and to cloath the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and to viſit the Priſoners of Jeſus Chriſt. Thou waſt as the Vine-tree amongſt the Trees of the Foreſt, Verily a Noble Vine; But why haſt thou ſo ſuddenly turned into the Degenerate Plant of a Strange Vine? Why of a right Seed did you ſo eaſily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſtrange Children, whoſe Mouth talketh Vanity, and your Right Hand is a Right Hand of Falſhood? Why didſt thou join thy ſelf with the Wicked, and help the Ungodly? Why didſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:63373:4"/>thou love them that hate the Lord, and didſt turn thy heart and hand againſt them that love the Lord? Thou didſt reject his Miniſters: thou didſt perſecute his People; thou didſt hunt the ſteps of the Righteous that they could not go in thy Streets; thou didſt hawll to Priſon the Aſſemblies of the Saints; and didſt make havock of the Church of Chriſt till there was no remedy.</p>
            <p>For when the Lord ſaw this he was angry, for he looked for Grapes from you, and you brought forth wild Grapes; he look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for Judgment from you, but behold Oppreſſion! for Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, but behold a Cry! <hi>Wherefore he bent his Bow againſt thee like an Enemy, He ſtood with his Right Hand like an Adverſary.</hi> He ſent a Fire into the midſt of thee that could not be quenched, and it hath devoured thee, and brought thee to Aſhes on the Earth, in the ſight of all them that beheld thee. He hath ſwallowed up thy Habitations, he hath thrown down in his Wrath your plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Dwellings, your ſtately and beautiful Buildings. He ſent into thee treacherous Dealers to deal treacherouſly with thee, and Spoilers to ſpoil thee; whilſt thou waſt become a ſilly Dove without heart. He hath brought upon thee the days that have not come on thee ſince thou waſt a City; He hath ſtained the Pride of thy Glory, and brought into contempt all thy Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Perſons: they that did feed delicately were left deſolate in the Streets; they that were brought up in Silks and Scarlet em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced Dunghils: they that dwelt in well built Houſes were glad to ſhelter themſelves in Booths, and to crowd their heads in deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late places; they are come down from their Glory to ſit in Duſt. For thy filthineſs was found in thy Skirts, therefore thou waſt brought down wonderfully. How are thy Merchandiſe of Gold and Silver, and Precious Stones, and of Pearl, and of fine Linnen, and Purple and Silk, thy broidered Works, thy Cheſts of rich Apparel, thy Spices and Odors, thy Veſſels of precious Wood, of Braſs and Iron, and Marble; thy Wine and Oil, thy ſtately Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and beautiful Structures of many Generations, how in three or four days are they all brought to nothing? <hi>London,</hi> the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Kingdom, the Beauty of <hi>England's</hi> Excellency, is become as when God overthrew <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah:</hi> and is now at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, a place for doleful Creatures, for Owls to dwell in, and for Satyrs to dance in, and for Wild Beaſts to cry among the deſolate Houſes, and Dragons in their Dwellings. For thou art ſwept with the Beſom of Deſtruction, and the Line of Emptineſs is ſtretched out upon thee; becauſe thou didſt reject the Word of the Lord, and kneweſt not the day of thy Viſitation.</p>
            <p>How art thou brought down, which waſt inhabited by Seafa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Men? the renowned City which waſt ſtrong at Sea? and thy Inhabitants did cauſe terrour to all Nations. All that knew thee formerly are aſtoniſht at thee; thou art become a Terror to them that ſee thee, and they that hear of thee are pained for thee. I was bowed down at the hearing of it, I was diſmayed at the ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:63373:5"/>of it. <hi>O Lord behold my affliction, for the Enemy hath magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied himſelf: ſee and conſider, for I am become Vile.</hi> Our Enemies ſay, This, this is the Day we have looked for; we have found it, we have ſeen it. This Day ſhall do that which the <hi>Fifth</hi> of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember</hi> could not do; now ſhall we ſee our deſire upon them; for the Strength of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Intereſt is broken; we have bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the Head of it, and now ſhall we raſe it, to the very founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it. But O Lord thou haſt ſeen my wrong, judge thou my Cauſe. Thou haſt ſeen all their Vengeance, and all their i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginations againſt me; thou knoweſt the Contrivers, the Abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, the Incouragers, the Actors, the Favourers of this Helliſh Miſchief; and all thoſe that rejoice in it: Give unto them All Sorrow of Heart, thy Curſe unto them. Perſecute and deſtroy them in Anger, from under the Heavens of the Lord. And let all the People ſay <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now I muſt ſhake hands with thee <hi>O London</hi> in thy Duſt and Aſhes, for there is hope in this thy End. And I muſt turn my ſelf back again to <hi>England,</hi> the Land of my Nativity, and take up a Lamentation for it. O <hi>England,</hi> what Nation was like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee from the Riſing of the Sun to the Setting thereof? thou waſt a People ſatisfied with favour, and full with the Bleſſings of the Lord, but art now ſuddenly become a poor and peeled People, meeted out and trodden down. Thou art ſmitten with a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſtroke in anger, by a heavy hand: thou art oppreſſed, ſpoyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and cruſhed in pieces evermore, and there is no man to ſave thee. For God hath remembred our Iniquities againſt us, and ſet our ſins in the light of his Countenance. For by Lying, and Swea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and Oppreſſing, and Slaying, and Drinking, and Whoring and Blaſpheming, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the Land is defiled, under the Inhabitants thereof. We have forſaken the Laws of God, changed the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of Chriſt, and broken the Everlaſting Covenant, and therefore hath the Curſe devoured us. Our Labours yield us no Profit: our Plowing, Sowing and Reaping eats up the Husband-Man: our Trade is every where decayed: our Gold and Silver are exhauſted and drained away: our Eſtates are impoveriſht and waſted: the Abundance we had gotten and laid up, is departed: our Exactions and Taxes are heavy upon us, ſo that we eat our Bread with ſorrow, and drink with ſighing; for they have found out our Riches as a Neſt, and as one gathereth Eggs that are left, ſo have they gathered the Subſtance of the Nation, and there was none that durſt move the Wing, or open the Mouth to the People. We are brought ſo low that we have forgotten Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; but we daily mourn and fade away, for we are filled with bitterneſs, and made drunk with Wormwood. For our Wiſe Counſellors are become Fools, Underſtanding is periſhed from them: our Princes are rebellious, and Companions of Thieves; they are Riotous Perſons that eat not for Strength but for Drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enneſs. Our Counſellors take Counſel, but not of God, but againſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:63373:5"/>him: our Judges abhor true Judgment, and pervert all Equity; they turn Judgment into Gall, and the fruit of Righteouſneſs into Hemlock: they juſtifie the Wicked for a Reward, and take away the righteouſneſs of the Righteous from him. Our Prieſts, of all Titles and Degrees, are like roaring Lions in the midſt of us, ravening the Prey; they rob the Purſes of Men; they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon their Bodies; they devour their Souls: they live in Riot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Drunkenneſs, they commit Adultery, and ſpeak Lyes: they ſtrengthen the hands of Evil Doers, that none doth return from his Wickedneſs. Our People are fooliſh and unwiſe, a company of treacherous Men, that ly-in wait for precious Souls; they are perverſe Children, who have forſaken the Law of the Lord, and have ſaid to the Holy One of <hi>Iſrael, Depart from us.</hi> Wherefore we are become a baſe Kingdom, becauſe we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected all righteouſneſs; yea, the baſeſt of Kingdoms, becauſe we have Apoſtatized from the Truth. Of a Pleaſant and Joyful Land, we are become a Land of Trouble and Anguiſh; where is the Young and Old Lion, the Viper and fiery flying Serpent. We are become a Mingled People, Strangers devour us in our preſence; they devour our Strength, they ſwallow up our Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, they eat up our Bread; yea they deſtroy us, our Cities and Towns, and there is none to reprove them. We who were the chief of Nations, the Princeſs of Provinces, who when we ſpake there was trembling to the ends of the Earth, are now become weak and contemptible; becauſe our Rock hath ſold us, and the Lord hath ſhut us up, Therefore the Pomp of our Strength hath ceaſed, and our Spirit fails in the midſt of us. So that we are ſhamefully brought down, by the leaſt and loweſt of the Nations: who have ſubdued our Naval Power; taken, burnt and ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed our Royal Ships, the Wall and Bulwark of our Nation: fought us in our own Bowels; triumphed over us in our own River; blocked up the Paſſage of our chief City; ſtopped all intercourſe of Trade; made a Spoil of our Riches, and a Prey of our Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe; hindred and deprived us of all our pleaſant things; berea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved us of ſeveral of our Rich and Advantageous Plantations; brought us down to their feet, humbly to beg their favour, and have made us a Reproach, a Proverb and a Hiſſing to all Nations. O <hi>England</hi> who ſhall bewail thee? What Lamentations ſhall we take up for thee? Oh that thou wert ſenſible of thy Stroke and couldſt bewail thy ſelf, for thou haſt ſinned grievouſly, therefore art thou caſt out of the Mountain of the Lord, thou art caſt to the ground, and laid before Kings and Nations, that they may behold thee. This is the end of the Children of Pride; for they that exalt themſelves ſhall be made Low. And therefore <hi>talk no more ſo exceeding proudly, let hot Arrogance come out of your Mouth again, for God is a God of Judgment, and by him actions are weighed. The Adverſaries of the Lord ſhall be broken in pieces: out of Heaven ſhall he thunder upon them, and therefore let not the Rebellious exalt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:63373:6"/>
            <p>Thus have Irehearſed the Evils we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y under; and now I ſhall repreſent ſome of the Great and Deadly Dangers that we are in.</p>
            <p>And one is, to have the Nation quire overrun with <hi>Popery,</hi> and to have the <hi>Popes Throne of Iniquity</hi> new erected amongſt us. And are there not ſwarms of <hi>Priests</hi> and <hi>Jeſuits</hi> earneſtly at work to bring this to paſs? they having emptied their <hi>Popiſh Cloyſters</hi> and <hi>Monaſteries</hi> from beyond Sea into <hi>England,</hi> to promote their <hi>Catholique Deſign</hi> here. And they knowing who ſtands at their right hand, have done it with great boldneſs, and with too great ſucceſs, For they have perverted not only very many of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon People, but ſome Nobility alſo, and many Gentry. And they have two great Engines to advance their deſign, to wit, on the one hand Safety, on the other Danger; on the one hand Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion, on the other Deſtruction; on the one hand Life, on the other Death; with the one of them they allure, with the other they terrifie; with the one they draw whom they can with the other they drive whom they cannot draw. And theſe Engines are of that force, that thereby they have conquered many weak, ſinful and unſtable Souls, yea and have prevailed with ſome Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Honour and Quality, to ſend their Sons to Monaſteries, and their Daughters to Nunneries beyond Sea, to be trained up in their Damnable Religion there, till better proviſion can be made for them here; of which they now are in full hopes.</p>
            <p>And now think with your ſelves, and conſider well, O my Dear <hi>Protestant</hi> Country-Men, how could you endure to ſee the <hi>Pope</hi> Worſhipped here again in <hi>England,</hi> for a God on Earth? to ſee him ſet his proud Foot on the Neck of your King? to ſee your King a Tributary to the <hi>Pope,</hi> and to ſtand or fall at his baſe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure? how could you indure to be forced to acknowledge his ſinful and fooliſh Decrees to be equal to the Holy Word of God? and to own his little Wafer, or piece of Bread, for the very Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Body and Bloud of Chriſt which was crucified and ſhed on the Croſs? how could you indure to have your throats ſtretched ſo wide, as to ſwallow down only this one Abomination of his, which is more vaſt and rude than the firſt Chaos? how could you indure to ſee new Roods erected in every Pariſh Church? and to bow your ſelves down and worſhip Stocks and Stones, Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixes and Images; inſtead of the True and Living God? how could you frame your ſelves to Auricular Confeſſion, and to rehearſe or enumerate all your ſins in a Prieſts Ear, who himſelf ſtands in need of Forgiveneſs more than you, being a greater Sinner? how could you indure that their luſty Prieſts ſhould defile your Wives and Daughters, they being prohibited Wives of their own; and ſo ſhould drive again a General Trade of Whoredom in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as they have been wont to do formerly? how could you ſubmit your ſelves to their <hi>Popiſh</hi> Pennance, and to travel their <hi>Popiſh</hi> Pilgrimages, to their feigned Saints and ridiculous Reliques?
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:63373:6"/>how could you bear the ſeverity of their Eccleſiaſtical Courts and Cenſures, and to be pronounced. Heretiques by thoſe who are themſelves the greateſt Heretiques in the World? how could You Noblemen and Gentlemen, who have your Eſtates, or part of them, in Abbey and Church-Lands, as they were called, be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to have them taken away from You and your Poſterity, and given back again to maintain <hi>Abbots, Monks, Friers, Nuns</hi> and ſuch kind of <hi>Popiſh Vermin</hi> and <hi>Locuſts,</hi> which, if once admitted, will eat up again every green thing in the Land? And let me tell you, that all theſe Eſtates of yours, they do not only promiſe to themſelves, but verily expect them. Yea farther, how could you indure to have your loving Husbands taken from your Heads, and your dear Wives torn out of your Boſoms, your ſweet Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren dragg'd out of your Houſes, your near Relations and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Neighbours hawlled and hurried into Priſons and Dungeons, and there to be wracked, ſtarved, tormented, and at laſt (if they live to it) to be put alive into the flames of Fire, there to be burnt and conſumed to Aſhes? and that only becauſe they ſincerely cleave to Chriſt and his Goſpel, and will not adhere to <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> nor receive his Mark, nor do his Helliſh Drudgery? how could you indure to ſee this cruel Beaſt of <hi>Rome</hi> to play <hi>Rex</hi> here in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> again; and though he be the Firſt-Born of the Devil, yet to ſet himſelf up above all that is called God, and Worſhipped? And yet you are now in more danger to ſee all theſe things come to paſs (<hi>becauſe you received not the truth in the love of it,</hi> whilſt you enjoyed it) than your Predeceſſors have been this Hundred Years, they having now gotten both Wind and Tide with them, even <hi>Opportunity</hi> and <hi>Incouragement.</hi> Wherefore a Great Man conclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>That now certainly the</hi> Papiſts <hi>would do their Work,</hi> they were in ſo fair a way. But he reckoned without his Hoaſt. And leſt my <hi>Proteſtant Country-Men</hi> ſhould be too much diſcouraged in this apparent and approaching Danger, I will furniſh you with one Rich Cordial, out of the Words of <hi>Henry</hi> the VIII. which he directed to the <hi>Papiſts</hi> in his days, in his foregoing Declaration againſt them: where he ſaith, <hi>Are you not wicked which ſo hate the Truth, that except ſhe be utterly baniſhed, ye will never ceaſe to vex her? The Living God is alive, neither can Truth his Darling, He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alive, be called to ſo great ſhame, contumely and injury as you would have her; and if ſhe may be called to all theſe, yet can ſhe come to none of them. Who is he that grievouſly lamenteth not! Men to be come to ſuch Shameleſs Boldneſs, to ſhew apertly that they be Enemies to Chriſt himſelf? on the other ſide, who would not be glad to ſee ſuch Men, as fooliſh as they be Wicked?</hi> For they work a deceitful Work, and by all their cunning Craftineſs, Myſterious, and Induſtrious Actings, they only dig the Pit, <hi>into which they muſt fall themſelves,</hi> and contrive the ruine that muſt be their own Portion.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:63373:7"/>
            <p>Your Second Danger, is to have the moſt Cruel and Inhumane Maſſacre executed upon you, that ever yet was committed in the World, by the Conſecrated Hands and Weapons of the <hi>Papiſts.</hi> And this Glorious Service of theirs is deſigned upon the <hi>Engliſh Proteſtants,</hi> for the ſingular Promotion of the <hi>Catholique</hi> Cauſe, which hath its way uſually prepared into all Nations, by Fire and Sword. The Wrath of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> is ſo kindled againſt you, and they are ſo thoroughly ſet on fire from Hell, that they are ready to break forth into their greateſt flames, and to endeavour the Deſtruction of All at Once. It is well known, how well they are Hors'd and Arm'd, and how they train their Troops againſt the Bloudy Day intended. It is well known, how well they are furniſh'd with Money, intended for other purpoſes. It is well know what numbers of <hi>French Men</hi> are brought into the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> and many Noblemen and Gentlemen are ſo pleaſed with the Children of thoſe Strangers, that they have <hi>French</hi> Servants, <hi>Papists,</hi> to attend them, whom they have well Mounted and Armed, enough to make a little Army of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. And this they do that their ſtrength may be hidden till opportunity ſhall ſerve to make it appear. It is well known that the chief Places of Strength, and many Chief Commands are in the hands of <hi>Papiſts.</hi> And now they become ſo numerous, and having ſuch power, what is there wanting but a convenient Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to fulfil all that is in their Hearts, upon Secure, Unar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, Unprepared People, and to diſpatch their work in few days, and eſpecially upon thee O <hi>London,</hi> who art their chiefeſt Eye-Sore. <hi>O England,</hi> (except the Lord prevent it) thy Calamity is near, at the very Door: and thou mayſt expect every day, now Peace is made Abroad, when theſe will unſheath and draw their Swords upon you here at Home: and you muſt be charg'd in the Kings Name (for ſo they will abuſe it) to ſtand ſtill, and to hold forth your Throats to Murderers. You cannot forget the dreadful Maffacre at <hi>Paris,</hi> nor that late more dreadful and blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Maſſacre of the <hi>Engliſh Proteſtants</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> when more than a Hundred Thouſand Innocent Perſons, Men, Women and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren were in a very ſhort time, with the greateſt Cruelties and Torments that ever were heard of, murdered by them; and what Authority they pretended for it. But they have treaſured up in their minds the fulneſs of all Cruelties, for you <hi>Engliſh-men.</hi> They have diſcovered ſomething of their Kindneſs and good Pleaſure to you in their firing the City of <hi>London,</hi> which they have left as an Everlaſting Monument of their Treachery and Villany to <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and of their hatred to <hi>Engliſh Proteſtants;</hi> and let this moſt notorious fact of theirs be engraven in great Characters on the Gates and Walls, and Chief Places of your City, when it ſhall be built again; that all Poſterity when they ſhall ſee New <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> may know and conſider what Perſons, and what Religion burnt the Old. They have alſo often attempted the firing of,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:63373:7"/>
               <hi>Southwark,</hi> and of the remaining parts of the City; for nothing but the utter ruine of it will ſatisfie them. And when the kindl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſome of theſe later flames, was related to a Great Perſon, they laughing ſaid, <hi>Now the Game is begun again:</hi> for they make but a <hi>May-game</hi> of conſuming all. And yet Fire only will not ſatisfie them, it is bloud muſt follow, or they are never the near. It is you <hi>O Engliſh Proteſtants,</hi> whoſe lives they thirſt after, and they can neither eat nor drink comfortably, nor ſleep quietly, till they be filled with this Veniſon. And therefore of you it may be truly ſaid, <hi>Your lives are in jeopardy every hour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet for all this let us not deſpond nor caſt away our Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, ſaying, <hi>Our hope is cut off, and we are periſhed;</hi> for he that ſits in Heaven laughs them to ſcorn, even the Lord hath them in Deriſion: and though we hold our peace, he will ſpeak to them in his Wrath, and vex them in his ſore diſpleaſure. He will make his Arrows drunk with their bloud, and his Sword ſhall devour their fleſh, from the beginning of Revenges upon the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. <hi>Rejoice O ye Nations, with his Paople, for he will avenge the Bloud of his Servants, and will render Vengeance to his Adverſaries, and will be merciful to his Land, and to his People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Another of your Dangers, which alſo is one of the greateſt, is your own Heedleſneſs and ſtrange Security, in the midſt of ſuch thick Clouds and Storms which have encompaſſed us round, able to awaken even dead Men. How ſtupid and ſott<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh were you at the burning of your City, when you ſaw with your own eies, your Houſes, your Subſtance, your Riches, all conſuming together in thoſe furious flames before your faces; yet how inſenſible were you of your deplorable condition? how regardleſs of that heavy hand of God? how inſenſible of the Treachery and Cruelty of Men? who did not only begin thoſe flames, but alſo continue them in the Progreſs they had appointed for them. Had you the Brains or Hearts of Men, to ſuffer thoſe Incendiaries who were taken in the very Act, to be reſcued from Juſtice, and releaſed to carry on their Villany again? ſurely you were ſo Sottiſh, that had not the Lord been the more merciful to you, your Lives and Houſes had periſhed together, as it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned. Moreover, how inſenſible have you been of the <hi>Popiſh Plot,</hi> and intended Maſſacre; as if thoſe good Men had been but in Jeſt, when a Regiment of <hi>Papiſts</hi> was brought up to ſecure the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and a company of Wolves to guard the Flock; and when ſome of their own Pens and Lips reveal their minds, why ſhould you yet be ſo ignorant of it, who are wholly concerned in it? Wherefore as your Lives hitherto have been dear to God, ſo let them now alſo be dear to your ſelves, and do not you ſay, <hi>Peace, Peace,</hi> when the <hi>Papiſts</hi> intend and prepare <hi>Deſtruction, Deſtruction;</hi> but let that be verified of you, which <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. ſaith of his time; to wit, <hi>The World is not now in ſo light a ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of you</hi> (Papiſts) <hi>as it hath been hitherto; but every Man ſeeth
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:63373:8"/>before his Eies, your deceits, your Wicked Minds, your Immortal Hatred againſt the Truth, and the Profeſſors of it, every Man ſees how many miſerable Tragedies your pretence of an Unity and Concord hath brought into</hi> Chriſtendom. <hi>They ſee your fair face of Peace hath ſerved Sedition, and troubled almoſt all Chriſtian Realms.</hi> And therefore ſeeing they were ſo quick-ſighted who lived above an hundred and thirty years ago, to ſee and foreſee the Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Cruelties of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> let not us who live ſo many years after, and have had far greater experience of them, be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together blind, and ſee nothing at all, in the clear Noon-ſhine of their Doings.</p>
            <p>Wherefore let all be admoniſhed, that after the deſired Tidings of Peace they be not ſo eagerly addicted to the rebuilding their Houſes, and regaining their Trade, and proſecuting their World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Affairs and Concernments (whilſt yet they are uncertain of the enjoyment of any thing) that they become careleſs and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardleſs how it fares with the Church of Chriſt and his Goſpel (which is the very light and life of our Souls, as well as the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of all our outward comforts) or how active and watchful the Brood of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> which lurks amongſt us, becomes, that they may deprive us of our Religion and Lives; and ſo, be as greedy Birds that are ſcratching for food, whilſt the Net is ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding over them to catch them at unawares; for what will it profit you to win Eſtates, and to loſe your Lives? your Lives are better than your Eſtates; and your Eſtates are but for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of your Lives. And if the Enemy take away your Lives, whoſe ſhall your Eſtates be? they ſhall even become a reward to the Murderers.</p>
            <p>Awaken therefore O. <hi>Proteſtants</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men out of your deep and dangerous Security! and ſtand upon your feet like Men: Ye dead men live again, and I will humbly and faithfully adviſe you (as I am able) out of very love, in a few things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. My <hi>Firſt</hi> Advice is, that you believe none of their pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed fairneſs and kindneſs to you, ſeeing their hearts are wholly againſt you, and their hatred to you is immortal; even the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of the Devil in the Hearts of Men, which is a certain fire of Hell which goes not out by Day or by Night. But know for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, when they promiſe fair, they are not to perform any thing, but the quite contrary: when they ſeem to kiſs you, they intend to kill you; when they ſuffer you to be quite, 'tis that they may bring the greater Trouble upon you; when they retreat from the exerciſe of their fierceneſs, 'tis that they return upon you with the greater Fury, when you ſhall leſs think af it; for their whole Trade is <hi>Deceit</hi> and <hi>Violence.</hi> Though Satan transform himſelf into an <hi>Angel of Light,</hi> yet ſtill is he is the <hi>Prince of Darkneſs;</hi> and theſe his Followers are exactly like him, both to deceive and to deſtroy: they will change their Colours, like <hi>Proteus,</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:63373:8"/>you, but they will never change their cruel Minds; but they that will be deceived, let them be deceived.</item>
               <item>2. My <hi>Second</hi> Advice is, that none either Plot or Attempt any thing againſt the preſent Power, but that all ſtand ſtill in their Place and Calling, like Wiſemen with their Eies in their Head, quietly waiting for the Salvation of God. For no Mans Hands can help him in this Matter, but our ſtrength is to ſit ſtill. We can no more change Kingdoms and Governments in the World, than we can alter the Courſe of the Sun or Moon in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens; but it is the Great God that muſt do theſe great things. It is the moſt High God that reigns in the Kingdom of Men, and gives them to whomſoever he will. And when his time is come, the ſet and full time, and the moſt High ſhall utter his Voice, his inſtruments ſhall be at his foot, ready to do his work, even to execute the Vengeance written; and all his mighty Providences ſhall concur, to bring about the Council of his Will. Wherefore remember, that Mans raſhneſs carrys ruin in it, but Patience per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects both Gods Works and Mans. <hi>In Patience poſſeſs your Souls.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Wherefore all that we would do, if we might be heard by thoſe that are inſtructed to help, at this needful Time is, only to deſire for the Glory of God, and the Nations good, and their own, theſe three things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That the dear and precious Goſpel of our Lord and Saviour may be permitted publiquely to be Preached again, in the Purity and Power of it, and that the faithful Teachers may be reſtored to their Miniſtry throughout the whole Nation. For when Jeſus Chriſt who <hi>hath all Power in Heaven and Earth given into his hands,</hi> hath commanded his Miniſters to <hi>go and teach in all Nations.</hi> How can you Worldly Powers, who have but a little Power in this Nation, anſwer it to him, when you forbid that to be done which he hath ſo ſolemnly commanded? He that <hi>hath all Power in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth</hi> hath commanded his Miniſters to teach his Goſpel, and dare you who have but a little power on Earth, and none at all in Heaven forbid them? If you do not repent of and amend this our Evils, it had been better for you, that you had never been born.</item>
               <item>2. Our ſecond deſire is, That all, <hi>Popiſh</hi> Commanders may be Disbanded, and put out of all Office and Truſt in a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Nation; and that all <hi>Papiſts</hi> through <hi>England</hi> may be diſarmed; ſeeing they are not armed for us, but againſt us.</item>
               <item>3. That all <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Outlandiſh</hi> Men may be baniſhed; for they are but Moths in our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Garment, to fret it by degrees, all to pieces; as they have fretted a great deal of it already.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:63373:9"/>
            <p>And what <hi>Engliſh-man</hi> or <hi>Proteſtant</hi> is there, that will not join with us in theſe neceſſary Deſires, which if they be not granted, farewel all Good Days from <hi>England</hi> for our time.</p>
            <p>And now to conclude all, I ſhall only leave two or three Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Antidotes with my dear Country-Men to preſerve them from the noyſome Contagion and Plague of <hi>Popery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Conſider with Trembling, that none are given up to this Damnable Deluſion but thoſe whoſe Names are not Written in the <hi>Lambs Books of Life,</hi> as the Spirit of God affirms <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.8. ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>And all that dwell upon Earth ſhall worſhip him</hi> (<hi>i.e.</hi> the Beaſt or Antichriſt of <hi>Rome</hi>) <hi>whoſe Names are not written in the Book of Life, of the Lamb ſlain from the Foundation of the World,</hi> And what Perſon would carry ſuch a Worm in his Conſcience continually, for the whole World, and all the Kingdoms and Glory of it, as to know and certainly to underſtand, that his Name <hi>is not written in the Book of Life,</hi> nor can ever be put in; for all the Writings in that Book are from Eternity, and no new thing can be inſerted in it. And therefore let Men ſay what they will, they are none of Gods Elect, who cloſe in with this Falſe and Heretical Religion, after the Goſpel hath been Preached to them, and they have been inſtructed in it. For to depart from the known Truth to known Error, is not a Sin of Ignorance, but of Malice; and this is the <hi>Sin unto Death,</hi> for which there is no Remiſſion. Wherefore let every one that would attain to any comfortable Aſſurance that his Name is Written in the <hi>Book of Life,</hi> flee from <hi>Popery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. They that Apoſtatiſe to this Falſe Religion, are as ſurely to be Damn'd as if they were in Hell already, This is a hard ſaying, but a True One: as it is evident in that of <hi>Paul,</hi> 2. <hi>Theſs.</hi> 2. where ſpeaking of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> that <hi>Wicked One, whoſe coming is after the working of Satan. with all Power and Signs, and Lying Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and with all deceiveableneſs of Unrighteouſneſs in them that periſh, becauſe they received not the love of the Truth, that they might be ſaved.</hi> He adds, <hi>And for this cauſe God ſhall ſend them ſtrong Deluſions that they ſhould believe a Lye, that</hi> they All may be Damn'd <hi>that believe not the Truth, but have pleaſure in Unrighteouſneſs-</hi> This ſort of People God gives them up to believe a Lye, the Grand Lye of <hi>Popery</hi> (for this whole Religion is nothing elſe but one continued Lye, from the beginning to the end of it) to the intent, that they ſhould all Periſh and be Damn'd. This is the Word of God, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all wilful <hi>Papists,</hi> and it cannot be made void. <hi>John</hi> alſo teſtifies <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.9. that an Angel Proclaimed with a loud voice, ſaying, <hi>If any Man Worſhip the Beaſt and his Image, and receive his Mark in his Forehead, or in his hand, the ſame ſhall drink of the Wine of the Wrath of God which is poured out without mixture into the Cup of his Indignation, and he ſhall be tormented with Fire and Brimstone, in the preſence of the holy Angels, and in the preſence of the Lamb;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:63373:9"/>and the Smoak of their Torment aſcendeth up for ever and ever: and they have no reſt Day nor Night, which Worſhip the Beaſt and his Image, and whoſoever receiveth the Mark of his Name.</hi> In which Scripture you may ſee with open face, the ſad end of all the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: which is to be <hi>tormented for ever and ever.</hi> Wherefore out of very Malice, they have been, are, and will be our Tormentors here, when they get opportunity, becauſe the Devil is to be their Tormentor in Hell for ever. Wherefore who ever would avoid the Torments of Hell let him fly from <hi>Popery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Laſtly <hi>Antichriſt</hi> is now in his Old Age, and draws near his End, yea is drawing his laſt breath. He is very ſhortly to be ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deſtroyed with the Spirit of Chriſts Mouth, and the Bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his coming. And what Wiſe-Man, yea what Man of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon reaſon would join himſelf to <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> for one hour, yea for one quarter or minute of his hour? If Men might have reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with him many years, and have enjoyed his Delicacies for a long Seaſon, then might it have been a ſtrong inducement to a carnal heart, who ſeeks his Portion only in this life, to have cloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in with him; but now to do it when his Deſtruction draws near, what extream Folly and Madneſs muſt it needs be? Who would venture a Board that Ship which is juſt a ſinking? or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Subject in that Kingdom which is juſt ready to be rooted up? and confident I am through God, that after Antichriſt and his Brood of Serpents, have play'd a few more of their old cruel Pranks anew in <hi>England,</hi> both He and They will become ſo ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly odious to All, that their Name ſhall be no more remembred among us, but with higheſt Contempt and Indignation, and that for ever. And let the Lord ſay <hi>Amen,</hi> and all his People.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:63373:10"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND now O Lord, to whom ſhould we look? our Eies are only unto thee. And we beſeech thee to look down from Heaven, the Habitation of thy Holineſs, and of thy Glory, upon us, and upon our preſent Sad, and almoſt Deſperate Condition: and ſtretch forth thy Holy Arm to maintain Thine Own Good Cauſe, (which thine Enemies ſcorn and deride, and laugh at among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) and to help afflicted Righteouſneſs, and thine own poor People, who are brought very low, ſo that their belly cleaveth, even to the duſt. Indeed, Vain is the Help of Man, and our Enemies ſay,</hi> There is no help for us in God: <hi>But yet we know there is help in thee, and that thy help is never in vain. For thou canst do the greateſt Things by the ſmalleſt Means, yea thou canſt do the greateſt Things, without all Means. For thou ſpakeſt and the World was made, thou didſt command, and it ſtood faſt. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Eies are unto thee, O Lord, and we do believe that thou canſt do all things; and can ſo do them, that none can reſiſt thee.</hi> Is any thing too hard for the Lord? <hi>ſhall we call thy Power in Queſtion, who didst prepare a ſafe paſſage for thy People through the mighty Waters, and didſt cauſe them to walk on dry ground through the depths of the Sea? Take therefore thy great Power and come and Reign in the midſt of theſe thy greateſt Enemies, till thou make them All thy Footſtool, and till thou hast put down all Rule, Authority and Power which lifts up its Head, and ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth its Arm againſt thee, O Lord, and thy Holy and Bleſſed Gospel, and thine Anointed. Oh cauſe Iniquity to stop its Mouth, and Wickedneſs to hide its face again. Let Violence no more be heard in our Land, nor Waſting and Destruction within our Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; let the cauſe of the Fatherleſs and of the Widows be juſtly judged, Let thy Priſoners be looſed, and thine oppreſſed be eaſed; let them be helped, who have no helper. Make way with thy ſtrong Arm for thy own</hi> Labourers <hi>to continue to come to</hi> thy Harveſt-Work; <hi>for thy Harveſt (we truſt) is very great in</hi> England. <hi>And therefore O Thou into whoſe hands all Things are delivered of the Father, and all Power in Heaven and Earth is given; and who by this Greateſt and Higheſt Authority of Thine, haſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded thy Miniſters, to go and teach all Nations, after thou didſt ſend them: Oh do thou make way for them to teach this Unworthy Nation, before the Coming of the Son of Man; that through their
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:63373:10"/>ministring thy Word, thy Church may awake and rouze up it ſelf, and put off its filthy Raiment, and may be reſtored to the Bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of its first riſing, when it was full of faith and love, and all Graces and Gifts of the Holy Ghoſt, without any mixture of</hi> Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian <hi>Errors, that all thy People may ſtrive together for the Faith of the Gospel, and not quarrel any longer about empty Forms; but may with One Mind, and with One Mouth confeſs the Truth as it is in</hi> Jeſus: <hi>and then ſhall all Kings bow down before thee, and all Nations that ſerve Thee, they ſhall ſing forth the Honour of thy Name and make thy Praiſe Glorious.</hi> Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
